Guide to the William Hillman Shockley Photographs, 1896-1922 and undated, bulk 1897-1909 RL.01177
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Other Places, 1897-1910; 31 prints
  - On board Mr. Mansfield's boat the "Amorita", last summer at Montauk, between 1903-1907 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1157)
    People on board a large yacht
    The Amorita was a 99-foot schooner yacht owned by a Richard Mansfield of Boston, who bought it in 1903 and sold it in 1915. [Source: New York Times, Feb. 1, 1903.]
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1931)
    Unidentified large buildings on corner of large intersection
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1932)
    Unidentified large building seen across a wide street and plaza in foreground
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1933)
    Street scene with horse-drawn carriage and delivery wagon
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1934)
    Detail of cornice above exterior doorway of unidentified building
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1935)
    Interior of room which chair and washstand (hotel?)
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1936)
    African American man in the street, pushing a sweeper bin on two wheels
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1937)
    Capitol building seen across a street and through distant trees
  - No known title, circa 1900 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1938)
    View of Capitol building from distance
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1939)
    Portrait of unidentified head of family, seated, in military dress-coat
    The man appears from visual inspection to be the same L.L. Wickham, mining engineer and supervisor of a mica mine in Nellore, India, featured in image RL01177-P-1292, 1899-1900. First name unknown.
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1940)
    Family group portrait, seated, wife, four daughters, and father, with family dog
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1941)
    Estate house seen across lawn
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1942)
    Girl running on tennis court
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1943)
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1944)
    Three girls standing together on tennis court
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1945)
    Father on tennis court
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1946)
    Three girls running on tennis court
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1947)
    Two girls and woman on croquet court
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1948)
    Woman, seated, reclining on furs
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1949)
    Two girls on croquet lawn, church and steeple visible behind trees
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1950)
    Family group, seated, wife, four daughters, father
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1951)
    Father covered with cheetah skin, playing with dog
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1952)
    Father reclining on lawn with dog, one daughter nearby
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1953)
    Family group portrait, standing
  - No known title, between 1903-1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1954)
    Two girls on tennis court
  - Manila / Ehrenffort [?], circa 1897 or 1902 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1955)
    Large single house behind picket pence, with U.S. flag on pole
  - No known title, circa 1897-1909 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1987)
    Large dredge on bank of river, unidentified location
    Found among loose, unidentified prints.
- Other Subjects, 1905-1920; 11 prints
  Portraits of unidentified babies and Shockley family members; some images are almost certainly May Shockley with their young son William B. Shockley in London. There is also a souvenir card with image of the god of happiness, Hotei.
  - Experiments, London, 1905 July 22 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1920)
    Unidentifiable image
    Unprocessed, reddish proof prints.
  - Experiments, London, 1905 July 22 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1921)
    Buildings, photographer's marks
  - Experiments, London, 1905 July 22 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1922)
  - Experiments, London, 1905 July 22 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1923)
    Boy in park-like setting, photographer's marks
  - Experiments, London, 1905 July 22 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1924)
  - Family, circa 1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1925)
    Two women with baby, seated outdoors
    Probably Shockley's wife, May, with only son, William Bradford Shockley, born February 1910; likely taken in London, where they lived at the time.
  - Family, circa 1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1926)
  - Family, circa 1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1927)
  - Family, circa 1910 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1928)
  - How do you do? Can you tell us apart?, between 1905-1915 (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1929)
    Twin infants, lying down, head shot
  - Hotei, early 20th century (Box 11, Print RL01177-P-1930)
    Souvenir black-and-white bi-fold pamphlet with image of smiling "God of good luck" statue on front, and explanatory printed message inside.
    Printed on back: "Yamanaka & Co. Inc. with locations in the U.S., London, Japan, and China." Inside has inscription about good luck and Hotei.
- Papers, 1897-1922; 1.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes
  Series includes a bound volume of roughly 100 carbon copies of correspondence dating from 1905 to 1922, written by W. H. Shockley from places such as Paris, France; London, England; St. Petersburg, Ivdell, and Bogoslovsk, Russia; Palo Alto, California, and Reno, Nevada. The majority of the correspondence relates to Shockley's work as a mining engineer, but there are also several personal letters to his wife and friends, correspondence relating to personal finances, short drafts of articles on mining in Russia, and notes from a correspondence course on the "Training of Children." The volume also contains several diary entries from 1922 and notes on the Kluchi mines in Russia. Four letters are in German.
  Also in the series is a set of three very small watercolor portraits of unidentified women, perhaps painted by Shockley's wife, May Bradford Shockley, who was an accomplished artist in addition to being a mining surveyor, an unusual career for a woman at the time.
  A manuscript notebook from Shockley's travels in India is housed in this series but more fully described in the India Photographs Series.
  Other Shockley family papers, including material relating to May Shockley and the Shockley's son, William B. Shockley, who was awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics for 1956 for his work on transistors, can be found at Stanford University's Special Collections Library in California. Photographs of W.H. Shockley and his Nevada family home can be found in the Walter F. Shockley Collection at the University of Nevada, Las Vegas.
  - Watercolor portraits, circa 1920 (Box 16)
  - Letterbook, 1905-1922 (Box 16)
  - Field notebook, India, 1899-1900 (see description in India photographs series) (Box 16)
  - Mica samples in envelope, 1899-1900 (Box 16)
    Mica samples are fragile and flake easily - please handle with care!
  - Original photograph envelopes, 1897-1910, 5 items (Box 16)
    Original envelopes, some with Shockley's handwriting, in which his photographs were stored.
  - Original glass dry plate negatives boxes, 1897-1910, 7 items (Box 17)
    Seven original dry glass plate negative boxes, all English brands. Some are labeled with the trip location.
- Original Negatives, approximately 436 items 3 boxes Glass plate negatives; nitrate film negatives
  Series houses an almost complete set of Shockley's nitrate film and glass plate negatives from which he made black-and-white contact prints and developing-out prints, during his travels and possibly after he arrived back home in London and the U.S. Some negatives do not have corresponding prints, and vice versa. The nitrate film negatives date from Shockley's later travels in Russia; it's likely they were created from the original glass plates when he returned to England, but this has not been verified.
  In the 2000s, a private collector and owner of the negatives created 8x10 inch glossy copy prints from the glass plates. A few dozen of these are unique images not found among the earlier prints, and are filed at the ends of the original print series to which they belong.
  About 20 film negatives reveal experimental images created by Shockley with double exposures and other effects; a few of these in print format can be found in the "Other Subjects" prints series.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Film and glass plate negatives are closed to general research use; access only by permission of Archive of Documentary Arts curator.
  - Australia, glass plate negatives, 1901-1902 [RESTRICTED], 32 plates (Box 18)
    Glass plate negatives, 3 1/4 x 4 1/2 inches, bearing images taken by Shockley in mining regions of Australia. One image of an Australian aboriginal young woman is unique to the collection; no print exists of it.
  - Russia, England, San Francisco - glass plate negatives, circa 1898-1909 [RESTRICTED], 134 plates (Box 19)
    Set of glass plate negatives, 3 1/4 x 4 1/2 inches, from which Shockley made the contact prints in main collection. There are a few unique glass plates with images not found elsewhere in the collection.
  - Nitrate film negatives, Russia, U.S., England, Experimental photography, 1905-1908 [RESTRICTED], approximately 270 negatives (Box 20)
    Set of nitrate film negatives, generally 3 1/2 x 4 1/2 to 4x5 inches, probably created from the positive prints in the collection. The set represents a good portion of the original prints taken in Russia. There are also a few dozen negatives for which it seems prints do not exist, taken in San Francisco, St. Petersburg (Russia), Southbourne (England), and London. A set of experimental exposures is also in the negative collection.
    The collection also includes glass plate negatives from which Shockley created the contact prints in the collection; these are also listed in the Negative Series.